{"tossups": [{"question": "In 2009, this country underwent the \u201cPots and Pans Revolution,\u201d a series of protests against Geir Haarde. This country planned to nationalize Glitnir, one of three banks that ultimately defaulted in 2008. During that financial crisis, the IMF gave this country a 5 billion dollar bailout to stabilize the<em> kr\u00b4ona</em>. For ten points, name this European country where mass protests took place outside the Althing in Reykjavik [rek-ya-vik].", "answer": "<b> Iceland</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "After this man\u2019s travels were abruptly ended by World War I, he returned to composing and produced <em>The Wooden Prince</em>. This man included the movement \u201cthe Fatherland is in danger\u201d and multiple refrains of \u201cGod save Franz the Kaiser\u201d in a work about an Austrian invasion,<em> Kossuth</em>. He was asked by Miklos Horthy to remove the name of Bela Balazs from his most famous work, which is about the namesake duke\u2019s fourth wife, Judith. For ten points, name this Hungarian composer of<em> Duke Bluebeard\u2019s Castle</em>.", "answer": "Bela<b> Bartok</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man began his writing career after facing exile following the fall of Amphipolis. In one work by this man, a winning army\u2019s diplomats state that \u201cthe strong do what they can and the weak suffer what they must.\u201d This man\u2019s most famous work includes the Melian Dialogue and recounts how the Delian League was led into war against Sparta. Pericles\u2019 Funeral Oration was recorded by, for ten points, what ancient Greek historian and author of a<em> History of the Peloponnesian War</em>?", "answer": "<b> Thucydides</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "During World War II, this state\u2019s leader allegedly kept a jar of eyeballs on his desk. This state was home to the infamous Jasenovac [YAH-sen-oh-vatz] concentration camp, where an estimated 20,000 Jews were killed. This state, whose flag featured a grenade against a white and red checker background, was led by a dictator with the title of Poglavnik, a translation of Fuhrer into this state\u2019s Slavic language; that leader, Ante Pavelic, was the leader of the Ustashe party, which murdered an estimated half million Orthodox Christian Serbs. For ten points, name this Yugoslav republic with capital Zagreb.", "answer": "<b> Croatia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A battle at this location resulted in the deaths of William Miller and Harold Stites and included a mortar attack ordered by James Johnston. Three residents of this location stole 50 raincoats to make an impromptu raft with the goal of reaching nearby Angel Island. Robert Stroud was labeled the \u201cBirdman\u201dof this location, where Al Capone was stabbed while incarcerated. For ten points, name this \u201cinescapable\u201dprison located in San Francisco Bay.", "answer": "<b> Alcatraz</b> Federal Penitentiary", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler established a detention camp for political opponents on Quiriquina Island. This leader\u2019s rise to power was assisted by propaganda run by the newspapers<em> La Tercera</em> and<em> El Murcurio</em>. A deputy of this leader, Manuel Contreras, was sentenced to extensive prison time for using the DINA secret police to assassinate dissident Orlando Letellier. This man orchestrated a coup that deposed Salvador Allende in 1973. For ten points, name this right-wing dictator of Chile.", "answer": "Augusto<b> Pinochet</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Rosenwald Fund was created to honor this man who, many years earlier, had been placed in charge of an Alabama institution by Samuel C. Armstrong. This man urged his followers to \u201ccast down your bucket where you are\u201d in an 1895 speech. This man was labeled the \u201cGreat Accommodator\u201d by his rival for his belief that African Americans should cooperate with supportive whites, rather than take more radical actions. For ten points, name this long-time opponent of W.E.B. DuBois who established the Tuskegee Institute.", "answer": "Booker Taliaferro<b> Washington</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this country, the Huks were a Communist guerrilla group that Edward Lansdale was tasked with putting down. The Moro Islamic Liberation Front also fought this country\u2019s government. In 1983, a president of this country had an opposition leader assassinated at an airport and was married to a woman famous for her large collection of shoes. Ferdinand Marcos led, for ten points, what Asian country home to the islands of Luzon and Mindanao?", "answer": "the<b> Philippines</b> (accept Republika ng<b> Pilipinas</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Inhabitants of this location participated in a contest to collect the first egg of the sooty tern as part of the Birdman cult, a motif that was also found in the glyphs of this location\u2019s rongorongo writing system. According to Jared Diamond\u2019s book<em> Collapse</em>, the loss of native forests in this location may have led to the downfall of the native Rapa Nui. For ten points, name this Chilean island where hundreds of<em> moai</em>, or large, stone-cut statues of heads, can be found.", "answer": "<b> Easter</b> Island", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This project was conceived in the Canandaigua debtor prison by Jesse Hawley, who was looking to boost the grain industry. The ship<em> Seneca Chief</em> brought water that Samuel Wilkeson poured into a lake at the completion of this project. Because it had the support of the governor, this project was known as that man\u2019s \u201cBig Ditch.\u201d Albany was connected through the Niagara Escarpment to Buffalo by, for ten points, what waterway that was completed in 1825 to help link New York with the Great Lakes?", "answer": "<b> Erie Canal</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One king of this name prohibited his wife from attending his own coronation, then introduced the Pains and Penalties Bill to annul his marriage to Caroline of Brunswick.</b> <b>While serving kings of this name, (+)</b> <b>Spencer Perceval was assassinated and Robert</b> <b>Spencer Perceval was assassinated and Robert</b> <b>Walpole became Britain\u2019s</b><em><b> de facto</b></em><b> first Prime Minister. (*)</b> <b>Walpole became Britain\u2019s</b><em><b> de facto</b></em><b> first Prime Minister. (*)</b> Porphyria [por-feer-ee-uh] was blamed for the mental illness of a king of this name. For ten points, give this British royal name whose third holder received the Olive Branch Petition from the American colonists.", "answer": "<b> George</b> (accept<b> George</b> IV throughout; accept<b> George</b> III starting at \u201cSpencer;\u201d accept <b>George</b> I or II starting at \u201cRobert\u201d) (2) <b>John Bly was hanged for looting during this event, but most of its participants were</b> <b>John Bly was hanged for looting during this event, but most of its participants were</b> <b>pardoned or given amnesty. Militiamen refused to fight for governor James (+)</b> <b>pardoned or given amnesty. Militiamen refused to fight for governor James (+)</b> <b>Bowdoin</b> <b>as he attempted to disperse protests in front of courts in Northampton and Worcester. The (*) </b> federal government failed to pay for an army to end this event, a rebel seizure of the Springfield Armory. For ten points, name this 1787 rebellion of disgruntled farmers in Massachusetts that highlighted the weakness of the Articles of Confederation. ANSWER:<b> Shays</b>\u2019 Rebellion (or Uprising, etc.; do not accept or prompt on \u201cShay\u201d alone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This mathematician proved that every Riemannian manifold can be embedded into some Euclidean space. This man, who once gave a presentation to the American Mathematical Society in which he claimed to have solved the Riemann hypothesis, was (+) killed with his wife in a taxi accident after receiving the Abel prize in 2015. The 1994 Nobel for Economics was awarded to this man for his work in (*) </b> game theory, specifically the introduction of his namesake equilibrium. For ten points, name this mathematician whose struggle with schizophrenia was portrayed in the film<em> A Beautiful Mind</em>.", "answer": "John Forbes<b> Nash</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A lynch mob in this state tortured Claude Neal in 1934. On Election Day 1920 in this state\u2019s town of Ocoee, whites killed over 50 African Americans and drove out the rest of the black population. The 1923 Rosewood massacre took place in this state, where the (+) NAACP\u2019s Harry Moore and his wife were killed by a KKK bombing in 1950. In 2012, police in the city of (*)</b> Sanford were criticized for not promptly arresting George Zimmerman, who shot and killed an unarmed black teenager. For ten points, name this state where Trayvon Martin was killed in a suburb north of Orlando.", "answer": "<b> Florida</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A poem about this man ends \u201cIn the prison of his days / Teach the free man how to praise,\u201d and references how \u201cIn the nightmare of the dark / All the dogs of Europe bark.\u201dAfter claiming that a certain author\u2019s work \u201cstirred [his] (+) blood,\u201d this man used the line\u201cThey seek not for hidden treasures, they know not how to cast nets\u201d in his introduction to Tagore\u2019s</b><em><b> Gitanjali</b></em><b>. This man, who \u201cdisappeared in the dead of winter\u201d but died on a (*)</b>\u201cdark cold day\u201d in a W.H. Auden eulogy, declared \u201cA terrible beauty is born\u201d at the end of a poem about a failed uprising against the British. For ten points, name this Irish poet of \u201cEaster, 1916.\u201d", "answer": "William Butler<b> Yeats</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The 1859 Pig War in Oregon began when a pig illegally ate this foodstuff and was shot. Antoine Parmentier\u2019s advocacy for this foodstuff included a scheme in which he posted guards around his farm, then told the guards to accept bribes from peasants</b> <b>wanting to take some. In 1992, (+)</b> <b>Dan Quayle was mocked for his failure to spell</b> <b>this word.</b><em><b> An Gorta Mor</b></em><b> is the native name for a (*)</b> disaster in which a<em> Phytophthora</em> <em>infestans</em> blight struck this food. For ten points, name this staple crop whose failure in the 1840s killed a million people in Ireland.", "answer": "<b> potato</b>es", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}